buying Vehicles just got a bit more
expensive in Singapore as the government
seeks to reduce the car population
buyers now have to pay as much as
$36,000 for the right to own a car
observers say rising demand from ride
hailing Services Uber and grab are
partly to blame Tony Waterman spoke to
the CEO of FWD Singapore recently to
find out how this trend is affecting
motor insurance premiums in the city
state
we actually think the Market's going to
soften a little bit more so just taking
our example we launched last year and
our proposition to the customer U is
twofold one n cd50 lifetime guarantee so
it's a full feature product and secondly
we don't distribute through Brokers or
agents or any middleman we go direct to
the customer so the savings we get from
the commission we pass on to the
customers now I think this would
actually set off a virtuous cycle in the
market where the industry will need to
respond with either Fuller featured
products and therefore better value for
the customer or lower prices so I would
actually think that the trends uh
southwards rather than northwards what
we've seen over the last couple of years
from uh 2013 2014 2015 is that the
actual number of cars on the road has
been falling it's been going down but
what we have seen that's quite
interesting is that from 2012 the number
of rental cars on the road has doubled
right is this the Uber grab ride hailing
service effect and how does that play
into premiums um the overall number of
vehicles going down is in line with the
government stated agenda they want
Singapore to be a car light Society over
a over a few years uh and I think over a
10-year time frame we would have roughly
320,000 private vehicles on the street
compared to 550 that we see currently so
that's going in the direction the
government wants it to uh the mix within
that is within the car has changed as
you pointed out so instead of outright
buying a private vehicle for themselves
they're actually leasing cars and using
them for Uber and grab as a secondary
commercial activity so I think as a
result what will happen is if if you
were a private car driver and you've
converted your car to a commercial use
which is let's say for Uber or grab the
premium goes up because the nature of
the use the vehicle is being put to has
changed the nature of risk has changed
the car is exposed to a lot more risk
it's on the streets a lot more so the
premium goes up for that particular
vehicle whether in the aggregate that
changes the you know moves the needle
for the market as a whole I don't really
know because there are these
counterbalancing forces the market size
itself is shrinking but then the nature
or the mix of the market is also
changing you know they say a true friend
is someone whom you can disagree with
and still remain